A Finding Aid to the Harold Baumbach Papers, 1934-1976, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Harold Baumbach papers
1934-1976
Archives of American Art
Baumbach, Harold, 1903-
AAA.baumharo
Archival Resource Key
0.4 Linear feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Harold Baumbach measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1934 to 1976. The papers document Baumbach's career as a painter and printmaker through correspondence, including with Adolph Gottlieb, slides and transparencies of Baumbach and some of his artwork, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and various art newsletters edited by Maud Kemper Riley.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reel 2147 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Baumbach (1903-2002) was a painter and printmaker from New York, New York.
Born in New York City in 1903, Baumbach was a self-taught painter who began exhibiting his work in the 1930s. Baumbach started with landscape painting, but gradually moved to a more abstract style. From 1946 to 1966 he taught painting techniques at Brooklyn College and was one of the founders of the journal Art Front.
Baumbach died in 2002.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 1977 by Harold Baumbach.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974
- Harold Baumbach Papers, 1934-1976; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Material consists of general correspondence and correspondence with Adolph Gottlieb and Edgar [Levy]; printed material including exhibition catalogs, announcements, and clippings; and slides and transparencies of Baumbach and some of his artwork. Also included are issues of Art Front, 1934-1936, and issues of publications edited by Maud Kemper Riley including Limited Edition, 1945, MKR's Art Weekly, 1946, and MKR's Art Outlook, 1946-1947.
  - Correspondence, Adolph Gottlieb, 1937-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Slides and Transparencies, circa 1955-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1937-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1960-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1937-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Art Front, 1934-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Limited Edition, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - MKR's Art Outlook, 1946-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - MKR's Art Weekly, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)